<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A New Location in Chicago</title>
    <description>Data Analysis and Future Work</description>
    <link>http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:12:19 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:12:19 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data Exploration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The type of business can make a difference in terms of taking advantage of the given data. In this analysis, I am assuming that it’s a bakery that needs a lot of in-store traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the brick and mortar retail businesses, there is much of a difference on how each can take advantage of the given data. For instance, a bakery can plan its menu according to whether it’s a weekday (more breakfast items) or weekend (more high-tea items). But a clothing store probably will not change its inventory accordingly. The additional data that we seek can also be different. A bakery might wonder about the demographic of commuters whereas an Apple store might not care as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the assumption of a bakery trying to expand into new locations, I proceed to explore the given data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data is a compilation of time series of number of rides per station. There are 147 stations total. Let’s take a quick look at stations and their respected number of rides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/all_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;all_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will certainly help if we can start a bakery near stations with the highest number of rides. However, we should not take the barcharts at face value. Let’s take a quick look at the box plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/box_all_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;box_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the chart, the stations with the highest rides can be due to outliers. As we explore the data further, it’s beneficial to keep that in mind. Also if the new location needs steady foot traffic, seeking highest mean and lowest standard deviation in rides might help. For now, we move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the time series plot of the top 5 stations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/max_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;max_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a moving average on the data to see if there is seasonality in it’s rides. To start a new location, inventory can be adjusted due to seasonality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/max_rides_ma.png&quot; alt=&quot;max_rides_ma&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a definite seasonality to the data. I wonder if it’s weather related? Or is it because people are out of town for Christmas? For now, I will make a note of it and explore that further in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a business, we should focus on opening locations with high foot traffic. But for completeness, let’s take a look at the stations with the lowest number of rides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/min_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;min_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This graph looks very different. It seems some of those stations didn’t get any rides until a later time – end of 2011. The station with lowest number of rides is Homan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/homan_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;homan_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought stations with a low number of rides because they are far away from downtown. But from the graph it looks like Homan is a brand new station! This is good news, perhaps the new location can take advantage of the possible lower rent near a new station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the next station: Cermak-McCormick Place. Interestingly enough, it looks like another new station (started in 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/cmp_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;cmp_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about one more? Oakton-Skokie station is the next station with the lowest number of rides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/os_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;os_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The station didn’t get any rides until 2012. But its number of rides dropped to 0 during the second half of 2015. I wonder why this is the case. Could it be because other stations opened up and it took a hit? Or a broken ride-counting machine? Or maybe construction blocked off the station? This begs the question of data integrity. Are the stations with the low rides really new or is it just because their machines are newly installed? If it’s the latter case, the new business might not take advantage of a newly developed area in terms of rent, then it has to go with the established areas with highest number of foot traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the data, there is also a column called daytypes. City of Chicago gave some answers. There are 3 datatypes: “W” for Weekday, “A” for Saturday and “U” for Sunday/Holidays. Plotting daytypes vs. number of rides, we see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/daytype_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;bar_daytype&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weekdays seem to a lot more rides. Verifying the finding with box-whisker charts:
&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/box_daytype_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;box_daytype&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, the weekdays still have more rides but not as drastic of a difference as what a barchart shows. However, notice that Sunday/Holidays have a lot of outliers. If we were to start a new location based on the rides per station, the next step will be to explore the daytype per station. Maybe some stations will have some interesting behavior over the holidays. Here is a first look at this information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/stacked_daytype_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;box_daytype&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This visualization is helpful. However, there is much information besides the given data that can help us. I will discuss these idea further in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:15:23 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//2016/data-exploration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//2016/data-exploration/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Further Research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From the initial exploration, we found the station with highest number of rides is Clark/Lake. The station with lowest number of rides is Homan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locating these two stations on a map will be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/stations_max_min.png&quot; alt=&quot;stations_max_min&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing the locations of these two stations, and knowing that the stations with low number of rides might be new, gave us some key understanding of a growing and ever expanding city. It will be great to combine the number of rides per station and locate them on a map. A very rough idea looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/map_barcharts.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;map_barcharts&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have witnessed the seasonality in rides. To see if it’s weather related, I can get the historical data  and compare. The weather data will look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/historical_temp_chicago.png&quot; alt=&quot;historical_weather&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coldest months are December/January. Does that coincide with the lowest number of rides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/max_rides_ma.png&quot; alt=&quot;max_rides_ma&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zooming in, the trough does seem to coincide with the lowest temperature in Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/cl_head_ma.png&quot; alt=&quot;cl_head_ma&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what about the folks who travel? Perhaps, they simply left town. We can look at airline data. For now, I will only include a link:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flychicago.com/OHare/EN/AboutUs/Facts/Air-Traffic-Data.aspx&quot;&gt;air_traffic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the data exploration, we have mentioned if a new location is looking for steady foot traffic, perhaps looking for a station with the highest mean and lowest standard deviation might help. First look at the mean vs stdev chart grouped by stations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/mean_std_rides.png&quot; alt=&quot;mean_std_rides&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just like in many other fields of study, there is no free lunch. As the number of rides increase, we are also witnessing an increase in standard deviation. Therefore, applying some optimization algorithm will help in identifying a few stations here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a bakery is to open a new location, demographic information will certainly help. One, the income level helps to determine the price point. Sell a slice of cake for $6.99 will not work in a low income area. There is a very good resource at &lt;a href=&quot;https://datausa.io/profile/geo/chicago-il/&quot;&gt;data_usa&lt;/a&gt; that will help in finding out more about the type of potential customers. The data that can be explored will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/data_usa_income.png&quot; alt=&quot;income_map&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Age, heritage and language will all need to be considered. Having time-stamp on the commuters data will also help the new location to anticipate the traffic.
Combining that with the station information, we will have a much better idea of where to start a new location. In particular, if near a busy station, during a certain time of the day, there are many kids, the bakery can prepare items that will be suitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that the daytype provided is only for workday vs. Saturday and holidays. We can also explore if there are variations among the week days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also explore proximity to office buildings around each potential new location. Not only can a bakery sell breakfast items, it can also provide lunches. The small circle represents the distance that commuters are willing to travel for during lunch break. The bigger circle represents the distance from station. The intersection is the area worth exploring. A rough plot might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/walking_office_station.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;walking_map&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming we are going to start the new location near a busy station. What about the nearby shops and competitions? I have included a google map here. Using an API will be something we consider in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/google_bakeries.png&quot; alt=&quot;bakery_map&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a few locations are selected, for example, we choose an area within walking distance to the top 3 stations, we will need to explore it further. Searching real estate rental prices is a must. The rental cost is an essential component in building up a financial model to forecast profitability of the new location. There are many API available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.programmableweb.com/news/40-real-estate-apis-zillow-trulia-walk-score/2012/02/15&quot;&gt;real_estate_api&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section, I will present a summary of this quick analysis and some thoughts on data presentation and modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:04:23 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//2016/further-research/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//2016/further-research/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Actions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We have taken a quick look at the given data. In summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data shows seasonality on both daily and monthly basis. Daily seasonality shows weekday vs. weekend/holidays patterns. At the monthly level, the data shows a drop of number of rides towards December/January time frame.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The stations with the lowest number of rides can be new stations. They might become worthy options to consider due to possibility of cheaper real estate rental prices (vs. the already established frequented areas).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weekdays tend to bring more foot traffic. However, depending on the station, Saturdays might have a great number of visitors as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stations with the higher total number of rides can have a lower average number of visitors. So one cannot take the total number of rides per station at face value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined with data on demographic, weather, air traffic, map, and time-stamp data, the original data set can be analyzed further to reveal key insights.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts on data presentation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because of the number of considerations, I would suggest to come up with a score for potential locations around stations. Clients can then decide on the location knowing the big picture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A score can be a combination of positive factors, such as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;proximity to busy stations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;proximity to office buildings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;high level of average disposable income (depending on the type of store)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;suitable demographic (goods dependant)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;stable foot traffic&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The negative factors can include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;high number of competitions in nearby areas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;high rental prices&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;long distance to port (if delivery is necessary)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;distance away from tourist areas (goods dependant)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The score can then be transformed with a sigmoid function and presented on top of a map. Here is a rough idea:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chicago_new_location/DataAnalysis/Images/scores.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;scores&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the scope of the project, clients can click into the score and receive the full back-ground information on how the score is calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts on models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using existing data such as existing store’s sales near the potential new locations as a dependent variable, along with the factors mentioned above as independent variables, we can construct a grid ready for modeling. Logistic regression based on cross-validation comes to mind. We can fine tune the model using Precision/Recall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more that can be done on this project. Clarification on the project scope and client’s final goal is important. Using the Agile method -  rapid prototyping and clear communication with the client - can help along with way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 09:03:23 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//2016/actions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://schen91020.github.io/chicago_new_location//2016/actions/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
